A Guide to the Horace H. Edwards Papers, 1941-1977
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Horace H. Edwards Papers, 1941-1977
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 246
12.2 linear feet
Horace H. Edwards
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated to the Department by Mrs. Mary Edwards in November 1987.
Biographical/Historical Information
Born in 1902 in Isle of Wight, Mr. Edwards began his political career shortly after his graduation from the University of Richmond in 1926 with a degree in law. In 1928 he worked on the presidential campaign of Al Smith. When Smith was defeated, Edwards returned to the practice of law but remained active in politics. In 1933 he was elected to the Virginia House of Delegates and served three terms. Appointed city attorney in 1938, Edwards held the position for ten years, guiding the city's direct annexation suits against Henrico and Chesterfield counties. In this period, Edwards became an expect on annexation and taxation.
Edwards was elected mayor of Richmond in 1946 and served for two years, resigning to seek the Democratic nomination for governor in the 1949 primary. During his unsuccessful campaign, Edwards spoke of more and better schools and better pay for teachers. In 1954 he accepted the position of Richmond City Manager, a capacity in which he served for thirteen years. During his tenure, Richmond began several construction projects. Although Edwards later admitted that he ran his office often without a certain amount of diplomacy, he survived three attempts by the City Council factions to oust him and became one of the city's most durable and effective administrators.
Following his resignation as City Manager in 1967, Edwards was named as special counsel for the city in its annexation suit against Chesterfield County. He also continued his work with the National and Virginia Municipal Leagues and the law firm of Mays, Valentine, Davenport and Moore. Mr. Edwards suffered a stroke in 1985 and was hospitalized several times before his death on 27 January 1987.
Additional information on Mr. Edwards can be found in the Pinchbeck Series, Good Government Awards 1959 materials of the Richmond First Club Archives, M238.
Scope and Content Information
The collection includes correspondences, reports, files and published materials dating from 1941 through 1977. The bulk of the collection dates from the 1950s through the mid 1970s and focuses on Mr. Edwards activities with the National and Virginia Municipal Leagues, the City of Richmond, the annexation of Chesterfield County.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Materials are arranged alphabetically within the series.
Organization
Series I--Personal Information and Legal Cases (1941-1977)
Series II--Holt Case (n.d., 1976)
Contents List
- Personal Information and Legal Cases 1941-1977
  - Address of City Manager Horace Edwards of the Virginia Municipal League 1963 (Box 1)
  - Address of Mayor Horace Edwards - Convention of American Municipal Association 1947 (Box 1)
  - Address of the Honorable Horace Edwards-League of VA Counties 1947 (Box 1)
  - Airport Study (Box 1)
  - American Election Systems 1970 (Box 1)
  - Annual Message by Horace Edwards, President to the Virginia Municipal League 1966 (Box 1)
  - Argument Docket-Supreme Court of Virginia at Richmond 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - American National Red Cross-Membership and Fund Campaign (Box 1)
  - Articles from the Times Dispatch about the Votes for Women (Box 1)
  - Assessment of the Work and Recommendations of the Virginia Metropolitan Area Study Commission 1968 (Box 1)
  - Babcock-Phillips (General File) 1969 (Box 1)
  - Beer vs the USA 1974 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Data on William G. Colman (Box 1)
  - Bradley vs the City of Richmond (Negro Composition of Area Schools) 1970 (Box 1)
  - Budgetary Controls in City Manager Government (Box 1)
  - Central Hill Baptist Church 1959 (Box 1)
  - Certificate of Incorporation of S. Bachrach Co., Incorporated 1968 (Box 1)
  - Chart Containing Tax Rate Applicable to Political Employees 1977 (Box 1)
  - City of Petersburg, Va vs the USA (Box 1)
  - City of Richmond vs. County of Chesterfield 1969 (Box 1)
  - Chavis vs. Whitcomb 1970 (Box 1)
  - Chavis vs. Whitcomb 1971 (Box 1)
  - Chesapeake Corporation vs. McCreery 1975 (Box 1)
  - Chesterfield Annexation (Appraisals) 1968 (Box 1)
  - Chesterfield Annexation (Bill for Interoogatories) 1968 (Box 1)
  - Chesterfield Annexation (Burnett Statement) 1969 (Box 1)
  - Chesterfield Annexation (General) 1969 (Box 1)
  - Chesterfield Annexation-Legal Memo (Valuation) 1968 (Box 1)
  - Chesterfield Annexation (Rountrey Appraisal) 1968 (Box 1)
  - Chesterfield Case-Supreme Court Option 1967 (Box 1)
  - Chesterfield County vs. the City of Richmond 1977 (Box 1)
  - Chesterfield Interrogatories (County) 1968 (Box 1)
  - Chesterfield Interrogatories (City) 1967 (Box 1)
  - City of Alexandria, Va-Service Award Program 1966 (Box 1)
  - City of Richmond vs. Chesterfield County 1975 (Box 1)
  - City of Richmond vs. County of Chesterfield 1968 (Box 1)
  - City of Richmond vs. County of Chesterfield (Annexation Suit) 1968 (Box 2)
  - City of Richmond vs. United State of America 1974 (Box 2)
  - City of Richmond vs. USA and Richard Kleindienst 1973 (Box 2)
  - Commonwealth of Virginia vs USA 1974 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (General) (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous Papers (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (Proposed Developments Facing the City) 1960 (Box 2)
  - County of Chesterfield (Summary of Tuition Chargeable to City of Richmond) 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - County of Henrico, Windsor Farms, Inc. and Others vs. City of Richmmond 1941 (Box 2)
  - County of Chesterfield, Va (Notes to Reconciliation of Net Operating School Cost for the Year Ended) 1970 (Box 2)
  - County of Los Angeles, California and the State of South Carolina vs. the Honarable Ray Marshall, The Honorable Michael Blumenthal and the Honorable Jerome Kurtz 1978 (Box 2)
  - Courts of the Richmond Area (A Primer) 1969 (Box 2)
  - Crime Statistics 1960-1965 (Box 2)
  - Data for Speech 1959 (Box 2)
  - Dedication Address of the Honorable Horace Edwards-City Hall-Waynesboro, Va 1962 (Box 2)
  - Dedication Address of the Honorable Horace Edwards-Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court 1964 (Box 2)
  - Deerbourne Civic and Recreation Association vs. City of Richmond 1969 (Box 2)
  - Deerbourne Civic and Recreation Association and Traylor Estates Civic Association, et al vs. City of Richmond 1969 (Box 2)
  - Department of Welfare 1956 (Box 2)
  - Description of Various Cases (Box 2)
  - Development of the Thesis that a City Reqires Balance to Survive 1970 (Box 2)
  - Development of Management Personal-Panel Participation Before Conference of International City Managers' Association 1954 (Box 2)
  - Digest of the Career and Achievements of Ben R. Johns, Jr. 1972 (Box 2)
  - Documents on Behalf of Defendants (Box 2)
  - DuVal, Clive vs. Prichard, Edgar (Box 2)
  - Edwards 1971 (Box 2)
  - Edwards, Horace (Miscellaneous) 1965-1968 (Box 2)
  - Edwards, Horace-Personal Information from Teaching (Political Science) 1969 (Box 2)
  - Edwards (Notes) (Box 2)
  - Edwards-Personal File 1951 (Box 3)
  - Edwards-Personal File 1953 (Box 3)
  - Edwards (President)-Virginia Municipal League 1966 (Box 3)
  - Election Statistics 1970 (Box 3)
  - Excerpts from the Remarks of Edwards- Civic Organizations and Municipal Government 1948 (Box 3)
  - Excerpts from the Remarks of Edwards-League of Virginia Municipalities 1955 (Box 3)
  - Excerpts from the Remarks of Edwards (President)-Virginia Section ICMA 1959 (Box 3)
  - Executive Director's Report 1969 (Box 3)
  - Federal Mandating of State and Local Personnel Practices: The Case for Caution 1977 (Box 3)
  - Federal and State Payments 1960 (Box 3)
  - Figures Used for Rotary Speech 1956 (Box 3)
  - Financial Report of the Director of Finance of the City of Richmond 1967 (Box 3)
  - Forward Thrust-Guidelines for Mobilizing Total Community Resources 1968 (Box 3)
  - Garbage Award of WRVA 1959 (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence-HHE 1968 (Box 3)
  - Good Legislative Session for Municipal Government 1966 (Box 3)
  - Hahn Commission 1967 (Box 3)
  - HHE-Correspondence 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - HHE-Correspondence 1972 (Box 3)
  - HHE-Correspondence and Miscellaneous 1972 (Box 3)
  - HHE-Estate of Russell Tinsley (See Also Tinsley Case) 1975 (Box 3)
  - HHE-George Scott-Sewer Line Problem 1975 (Box 3)
  - HHE-Memos 1972 (Box 3)
  - HHE-Personal Correspondence 1974 (Box 3)
  - HHE-Trial Notes-Chesterfield 1971 (Box 3)
  - ICMA 1967 (Box 3)
  - Idea and Assignment Sheet 1975-1977 (Box 3)
  - Impact of Annexation on City Finances: A Case Study in Richmond, Virginia 1971 (Box 3)
  - The Importance of Effective Tax Collecting (Box 3)
  - Index of Witnesses (Cith of Richmond vs. Chesterfield County) 1969 (Box 3)
  - Isle of Wight 1966 (Box 3)
  - Junes' Papers 1979 (Box 4)
  - Junes' (Louis and Thalia) Papers 1980 (Box 4)
  - Laws for Certain Cities in Certain States (Box 4)
  - List of Legislative History Materials 1977 (Box 4)
  - The Magazine of Virginia Commonwealth 1983 (Box 4)
  - Mahan, John vs. Howell, Henry vs. City of Va Beach vs. Howeel vs. Weinberg vs. Prichard 1971 (Box 4)
  - Manager Evaluates Modern Budget Practices 1956 (Box 4)
  - Materials for an Accounting Class 1961 (Box 4)
  - Material on the Internal Revenue Service 1976 (Box 4)
  - McCreery Case-Chronology 1976 (Box 4)
  - McCreery vs the Chesapeake Corporation 1977 (Box 4)
  - Memo File 1971 (Box 4)
  - Memorandum (To: Mr. Crosley From: Lang Smith) (Box 4)
  - Memorandum on the Proposed Compromise in the Chesterfield County Annexation Line Relating to Richmond City School Building Needs 1969 (Box 4)
  - Memorial Resolution (John Davis) 1969 (Box 4)
  - Minutes of the Meeting of the Council of the National Municipal League 1969 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous-HHE 1971 (Box 4)
  - Municipal Annexation: The Federal Dimension 1976 (Box 4)
  - Name and Address List for Lawyers in the Firm 1983 (Box 4)
  - National Association for Community Development vs. Hodgson 1973 (Box 4)
  - National Municipal League 1970 (Box 4)
  - National Municipal League Conference 1954 (Box 4)
  - National Municipal League-Financial Statements (Report of Certified Public Accountants) 1967 (Box 4)
  - National Municipal League-Financial Statements (Report of Certified Public Accountants) 1968 (Box 4)
  - National Municipal League-Financial Statements (Report of Certified Public Accountants) 1969 (Box 4)
  - National Municipal League (Statement of Assets, Liabilities and Fund Balances) 1969 (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Article- Shift Debated in Voting Rights 1971 (Box 4)
  - Notes-Edwards (Box 4)
  - Notice of Special Meeting of Shareholders 1976 (Box 4)
  - Notes on League Speech at the Chamberlain (Box 4)
  - Notes for Talk at ASPA Convention 1956 (Box 4)
  - Oath of the Citizens of Athens (Box 4)
  - Off-Street Parking 1961 (Box 4)
  - Optimist Club of Emporia, Va 1955 (Box 4)
  - Option to Purchase 1977 (Box 4)
  - Paper on Thomas Jefferson (Box 4)
  - Party Responsibility (Address at Jefferson Day) 1953 (Box 4)
  - Pamphlets on the National Municipal League 1968-1970 (Box 4)
  - Planning for a Greater Richmond (Box 4)
  - Planning and Urban Development-City Exhibits-City of Richmond vs. USA (Box 4)
  - Problems of Local Government 1916-1955 (Box 4)
  - Recommendations for Changes in Richmond Supplemental Retirement System (Box 5)
  - Remarks of the Honorable Thomas Bliley (Mayor of Richmond) 1976 (Box 5)
  - Report to Henrico County and Chesterfield County, VA (Box 5)
  - Richmond Bar-Committee on Legislation 1971 (Box 5)
  - The Richmond-Petersburg Turnpike Authority 1968 (Box 5)
  - Richmond vs. Chesterfield (Capital Budget) 1968 (Box 5)
  - Richmond vs. Chesterfield (General Services) 1971 (Box 5)
  - Richmond vs. Chesterfield (Planning) 1969 (Box 5)
  - Richmond vs. Chesterfield (Public Works) 1969 (Box 5)
  - Richmond vs Chesterfield (Recreation) 1969 (Box 5)
  - Richmond vs. Chesterfield (Sewers-County) 1967 (Box 5)
  - Richmond vs. Chesterfield (Water-County) 1968 (Box 5)
  - Richmond vs Chesterfield (Welfare) 1968 (Box 5)
  - Richmond, Va 1969 (Box 5)
  - Richmond Urban Institute (See also search) (Box 5)
  - Rotary Club Speech-Comparisons (Negro and White) 1956 (Box 5)
  - Rotary Speech 1966 (Box 5)
  - RPI-Evening College 1971 (Box 5)
  - The Slavation Army (Hospital Advisory Council) (Box 5)
  - School Board of Chesterfield County vs. School Board of the City of Richmond 1974 (Box 5)
  - School Board of Chesterfield County vs School Board of the City of Richmond 1976 (Box 5)
  - School Board of Chesterfield County vs. School Board of the City of Richmond 1976-1977 (Box 5)
  - School Board of Chesterfield County vs. School Board of the City of Richmond 1977 (Box 5)
  - Scientific American-Magazine (September) 1965 (Box 5)
  - Search-A Report from the Richmond Urban Institute 1975 (Box 5)
  - Series of Poems 1966 (Box 5)
  - Service Pin Awards 1956 (Box 5)
  - Significant Developments Facig the City of Richmond 1960 (Box 5)
  - Social Security Act of 1935: Congressional Debates (Box 5)
  - Sound Municipal Insurance Program 1960 (Box 5)
  - Speech-50 Years of Municipal Government in the US 1965 (Box 5)
  - Speech Material 1967 (Box 5)
  - Speech Material-Bureau of Police (Box 5)
  - Speech Material-Urban Trends in the General Assembly (Box 5)
  - State Constitutional Conventions 1968 (Box 5)
  - State Constitutional Conventions 1969 (Box 5)
  - State Constitutional Conventions 1970 (Box 5)
  - State Legislature Progress Report 1969 (Box 5)
  - State Legislatures Project (3rd Annual Report) 1968 (Box 5)
  - State Legislatures Project (4th Annual Report) 1969 (Box 5)
  - State Legislatures Project (5th Annual Report) 1970 (Box 5)
  - State Sales Tax 1956 (Box 5)
  - Statistics on GNP (Box 5)
  - Status of the City (Fiscal and Management Report) 1973-1977 (Box 6)
  - Stockholders in Government (Box 6)
  - Strengthening Management Organization-The City of Richmond 1971 (Box 6)
  - Summary of Testimonies 1975 (Box 6)
  - Supplement-Powers of Cities and Towns (Box 6)
  - Tinsley Case 1975 (Box 6)
  - Tuckev Club-Separation of the Church and State 1959 (Box 6)
  - Unemployment Insurance Costs to Local Government in State of Va and Cost to State of Va (Box 6)
  - United States District Court for the District of Columbia (Box 6)
  - University of Richmond-Law Review (Box 6)
  - Urban Renewal in Richmond 1962 (Box 6)
  - Usher's Speech 1956 (Box 6)
  - Virginia Municipal League (Box 6)
  - Virginia Society for Crippled Children and Adults-Richmond Chapter 1951 (Box 6)
  - Virginia State Bar 1969 (Box 6)
  - Virginia Union University-Summer Session (Box 6)
  - Welfare Statistics 1966 (Box 6)
  - Virginia Union University-Summer Session (Box 6)
  - Welfare Statistics 1966 (Box 6)
  - Youth City Government 1958 (Box 6)
- Holt Case
  - Annexation of Virginia (book) by Chester W. Bain (Box 7)
  - Briefs I of IV and II of IV (Box 7)
  - Briefs III of IV of IV (Box 7)
  - Briefs on Annexation Case (#1) (Box 7)
  - Briefs on Annexation Case (#2) (Box 7)
  - Briefs on Annexation Case (#3) (Box 7)
  - Briefs on Annexation Case (#4) (Box 7)
  - Briefs on Annexation Case (#5) (Box 7)
  - Briefs on Annexation (#6) (Box 8)
  - Briefs on Annexation (#7) (Box 8)
  - City of Richmond Exhibits (Box 8)
  - City of Richmond Proposed Five Year Capital Improvement Plan (Box 8)
  - Correspondence on Annexation (Box 8)
  - Maps of Annexation and Corresponding Statistics (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Materials on Annexation (#1) (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Materials on Annexation (#2) (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Materials on Annexation (#3) (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Materials on Annexation (#4) (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous Materials on Annexation (#5) (Box 9)
  - Notes on Annexation (Written by Edwards) (Box 9)
  - Plan of Government for the Richmond Region (Box 9)
  - Statistics of Annexation (Box 9)
  - Transcript on Holt Case January 15, 1976 (Box 9)
  - Various Original Briefs on Holt Case (#1) (Box 9)
  - Various Original Briefs on Holt Case (#2) (Box 10)
  - Various Original Briefs on Holt Case (#3) (Box 10)
  - Various Original Briefs on Holt Case (#4) (Box 10)
  - Various Original Briefs on Holt Case (#5) (Box 10)